A Guide to the Papers of the Carter and Wellford Family of Sabine Hall 1650-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series VI: Correspondence of Armistead Nelson Wilford
  - Edward Thornton Tayloe to Armistead Nelson Wellford 1873 June (Box-folder 4:4)
    bond requested by the Warings; Kate's ill health; Anne may not be able to leave home to go to Sabine Hall because of delicate nature; good quality of wheat crops
  - Edward Thornton Tayloe to Armistead Nelson Wellford 1873 September 8 (Box-folder 4:4)
    informed of Kate's death by Judge Lewis; necessity of closing their trusteeship; praise of her character
  - William L. Clark to Armistead Nelson Wellford 1873 December 29 (Box-folder 4:4)
    attempting to collect from the present holder of the Carter tract; debts to the Carter estate
  - George W. Lewis to Armistead Nelson Wellford, with letter from Robert Y. Conrad & Son and lists of Confederate States registered certificates 1874 January 12 (Box-folder 4:4)
    negative comments on the County Court system and General Assembly; debt of Col. Frank Jones to the Carter estate
- Series VII: Correspondence of Robert Carter Wellford and Armistead Nelson Wellford
  - Cassius Francis Lee, Jr. to Robert Carter Wellford 1889 September 26 (Box-folder 4:5)
    offer for letters of George Washington, Robert E. Lee, Richard Henry Lee, Francis Lightfoot Lee, and others; describes content of some letters
  - 1889 October 8 (Box-folder 4:5)
    describes deteriorating condition of some letters
  - Cassius Francis Lee, Jr. to Robert Carter Wellford 1889 October 22 (Box-folder 4:5)
    offers on group of letters, including from Washington, and Gov. Gooch and Faquier, and a copy of Sir Henry Clinton's proclamation; inquires as to whereabouts of Col. John Tayloe's papers
  - Cassius Francis Lee, Jr. to Robert Carter Wellford 1889 November 5 (Box-folder 4:5)
    received Gooch, Fauquier and Squire Lee letters; read account of the silver spoons; John Tayloe's daughter married Francis Lightfoot Lee and acquired "Menokin"; inquires again about the whereabouts of John Tayloe's papers
  - Cassius Francis Lee, Jr. to Robert Carter Wellford 1889 November 27 (Box-folder 4:5)
    returns one bundle of letters; advises that the letters should never be folded but laid out flat and open; inquires about "Landsdowne," home of Arthur Lee and the old mansion where Francis Lightfoot Lee used to live
  - Correspondence of Armistead Nelson Wellford and Earl G. Swem of the Library of William and Mary College 1935-1936 (Box-folder 4:5)
    instructed by John Stewart Bryan, president of William and Mary, to offer $500 for the letters offered to the Library; wish to preserve Virginia manuscripts; identification of writers of some letters; list, 1892, of letters sold by Robert Carter Wellford and another handwritten list enclosed; whereabouts of the Havemeyer collection; Duke University may have bought Havemeyer collection; copy of the inventory of Landon Carter I
- Series VIII: Financial Papers of the Carter and Wellford Families
  - Estate of Landon Carter: Accounts, primarily pertaining to land and inheritance of Robert Wormeley Carter 1783 March-1808 June 27 (Box-folder 4:6)
    Estate of Landon Carter in account with the Estate of the Rt. Hon. Thomas Fairfax; taxable property of Robert Wormeley Carter
  - Old Dominion Steam Boat Company Stocks and Shares of Robert Wormeley Carter 1852-1861 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - White Sulphur Springs Shares and Bonds of Robert Wormeley Carter 1858-1859 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Civil War Bonds for the sum of $1000 1861 (Box-folder 4:9)
    issued to and signed by Jeremiah Morton, Allen Taylor Caperton, John Prosser Tabb, Robert Wormeley Carter, Richard Henry Dulaney, Robert B. Bolling, and Philip St. George Cocke; bonds were later signed over to Douglas H. Gordon, and A. F. Taylor
  - Estate of Robert Wormeley Carter: Accounts 1855-1861 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Estate of Robert Wormeley Carter: Accounts 1862 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Estate of Robert Wormeley Carter: Accounts 1863-1869 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Estate of Robert Wormeley Carter: Accounts 1870-1918 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Estate of Robert Wormeley Carter: Mays Bankruptcy 1857-1869 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Estate of Robert Wormeley Carter: Inheritance of Anne Catharine Carter 1869-1871 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Day Book and Ledger kept by Robert Wormeley Carter 1858-1861 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Day Book kept by Robert Wormeley Carter 1860-1861 (Box-folder 4:17)
    in account with Armistead Nelson Wellford and Beverley R. Wellford and the Bank of Virginia
  - Confederate States of America vouchers for one hundred dollars and Bonds of Armistead Nelson Wellford 1862-1863 (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Parole and Pardon for Armistead Nelson Wellford from Andrew Johnson, the president of the United States of America 1865
  - Day Book with Bank of Virginia account, kept by Armistead Nelson Wellford 1862-1864 (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Day Books kept by Armistead Nelson Wellford 1860-1866, 2 volumes (Box-folder 4:20)
  - Day Books kept by Armistead Nelson Wellford 1867-1879, 5 volumes (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Anderson Brothers Bookstore Receipts to Armistead Nelson Wellford 1898-1900 (Box-folder 5:2)
- Series IX: Legal Papers of the Carter Family
  - Survey maps and descriptions of 483 acres, 277 acres, and 1561 acres in Northumberland County 1784 May 3 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Survey maps and descriptions of acreage in Northumberland County 1784 May (Oversize Oversize)
    made by Griffin Garland for Robert Wormeley Carter
  - Indenture, Richard Neale, Henry and Margaret Garrett et al 1787 January 18 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Extracts of legal documents pertaining to Broad Run Tract owned by Robert Carter 1788 April 9 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Map and survey of property belonging to Col. William Lee 1789 July 12 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Map and survey of Col. William Lee's land 1789 July 13 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Survey map and description of 760 acres of land made by Benjamin Garland for William and Harry Harford 1793 December 5 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Rawleigh Tapscott Survey of mill property belonging to Landon Carter II 1805 February 12 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Indenture between Peter Rust, Vincent Bramham and Bartholomew McCarty, and Landon Carter for property known as "Juggs" 1810 March 12 (Box-folder 5:3)
    Rust desires Carter to release his claim on the tract of land; Carter has consented; agreement to sell land to William L. Waring and John Waring; agreement to sell negro slaves Sarah and her daughter, Wennie, to Bramham and McCarty
  - Indenture between Peter Rust, Vincent Bramham and Bartholomew McCarty, and Landon Carter for property known as "Juggs" [see March 12, 1810] 1810 July 21 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Remarks on Lampkin's survey of Sabine Hall estate [1820] (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Survey of 7440 acres in Frederick County made by William Castleman for the heirs of Landon Carter II 1821 August 8 (Oversize Oversize)
  - William Castleman's survey of land in the Shenandoah River belonging to the heirs of Landon Carter II 1821 September 22 (Oversize Oversize)
  - William Castleman's survey of land in the Shenandoah River belonging to the heirs of Landon Carter II 1821 September 22 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Indenture, Francis and Lettice Smith to Robert Carter for property in Richmond County by Jugg Creek, with all buildings, structures and pastures 1822 August 7 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Extract from the Deed of Landon Carter to William Y. Weathers 1824 May 12 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Deed for Sabine Hall: Indenture between Elizabeth L. Carter and Robert Wormeley Carter 1824 July 23 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Indenture between Landon Carter, Jr. and John Minor for acreage of Sabine Hall, Richmond County 1826 March 13 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Indenture between John Minor, trustee of Landon Carter, Jr., and Robert Wormeley Carter for acreage of Sabine Hall, Richmond County 1830 April 13 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Indenture between the Commissioners of the estate of Henry Harford and Robert Wormeley Carter for property in Richmond County 1835 March 2 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Stock Certificates for the Manchester Cotton and Wool Manufacturing Company, along with notes due for stock and promissory notes 1836-1839, 11 items (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Deed of Trust: Indenture, William Younger Weather to John F. B. Jeffries, with excerpt of 1824 deed, for property in Richmond County 1839 February 5 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Stock Certificates for shares in banks in the State of Virginia: Bank of Commerce, Exchange Bank of Virginia and Farmers Bank of Virginia 1849-1860, 14 items (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Henry Clarke Survey of unknown home done for the Protection Insurance Company [184 ] (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Report from David Stewart to Robert Wormeley Carter 1852 March 2 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Egerton & Brothers, Baltimore Maryland Circular of the Maryland Lotteries 1852 October 1 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - COSMO Circular for sale of Cosmo by imported Skylark, dam by the famed imported Priam 1853 March 9 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Indenture between the White Sulphur Springs Company, Greenbrier County, and Robert Wormeley Carter 1858 December 24 (Box-folder 5:4)
    with certain provisions, and granting forever the fourth cottage in Baltimore Row under said terms and limitations
  - Deed between James M. and Mary Ann Morgan with Francis W. Pendleton for property in the village of Warsaw, Richmond County 1860 November 3 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Deed between J. Horace and Betty C. Lacy and William A. Little for property known as "Chatham," Stafford County, held in trust to secure payment to a bond executed by Robert Wormeley Carter (and copy) 1861 February 1 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Affidavit of William H. Morris that he has lived next to "Wilna," the property of Armistead Nelson Wellford and acted as manager for Wellford 1863 January 4 (Box-folder 5:5)
    five negro slaves to wit Bladen, John, Frank, Randal and Phil belonging to Wellford together with negroes from A. H. H. Bernard and Benjamin R. Baird absconded from their owners in a small boat down the Rappahannock River
  - Affidavit of Jordan B. Lowry that he is the manager of "Sabine Hall" 1863 December 7 (Box-folder 5:5)
    three negro men slaves to wit Elias, William and Jesse left under circumstances that predict that they went to the public enemy; good character and work traits of these slaves; two negroes to wit Harry and Daniel ran away to the north side of the Tappahannock River; draft of Wellford's statement to Lowry
  - Article of Agreement between Armistead Nelson Wellford and Thomas Gates binding the latter to serve faithfully and truly to Wellford 1866 January 1 (Box-folder 5:5)
    rules and regulations for said employee
  - Presents entered between Armistead Nelson Wellford and Walter J. Ramis 1868 November 24 (Box-folder 5:5)
    to hire the latter to construct and lay down a causeway across Jugs Creek and permission to use said causeway
  - Contract between Armistead Nelson Wellford and Henry S. Renzir leasing to the latter the farm known as "Old Fork" 1869 August 10 (Box-folder 5:5)
    terms and conditions of lease
  - Acknowledgment of John A. Carter of holding bonds of Jacqueline A. Marshall and John T. Grant payable annually to Armistead Nelson Wellford and George W. Lewis 1872 May 21 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Memorandum of Agreement witness that Armistead Nelson Wellford has agreed to pay on Tayloe's account to George W. Lewis 1874 January 1 (Box-folder 5:5)
    Edward Thornton Tayloe desires to secure the repayment of the sum
  - List of Judgments rendered in Circuit Court of Richmond County in favor of Robert Wormeley Carter's estate 1875 (Box-folder 5:5)
    judgments covering the years 1860-1875
  - Deed of Maria Murphy, daughter of Fauntleroy and heir to the Island, to Brockenbrough 1894 (Box-folder 5:5)
    stating that she has rented the marsh shore as a fishing shore and the marsh for game of all kinds; notice to stop using land
  - Legal papers relating to the petition of the White Sulphur Springs Company for the lease of the property 1866-1875 (Box-folder 5:6)
- Series X: Miscellaneous
  - Journal of Robert Wormeley Carter I 1783 January-1784 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Journal of Robert Wormeley Carter II 1812 October-1814 November (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Broadside declaring Henry Lee, Jr.'s candidacy for Congress (copy and transcripts) 1816 October 28 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Essays, Poems, and Songs 1825, 1849, 1861, n.d. (Box-folder 5:9)
    "In imitation of Burn's Lassie we the lint-while Cocks" "Lines on revisiting Jordan's Springs" by Robert Wormeley Carter; An old "Scotch Ballad"; "Leaves from the Note Book of an old Virginia Plantation"; and a brief essay on the American Revolution
  - Commonplace Book kept by Elizabeth M. Tayloe; Inventory of Household Articles, 1830, kept by Robert Wormeley Carter 1827-1875 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - "Poems by Imogene" 1833-1834 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - 1836 November 10 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Richmond County Election Returns 1836 November 12 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Senatorial polls taken at Richmond Court House for Robert Wormeley Carter, with 1836 memoranda of the presidential election 1837 April 27 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Genealogical Data on the Carter, Tayloe and Corbin families 1840 (1852-1854) (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Parole of Honor signed by Armistead Nelson Wellford 1865 April 25 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Certification of Oath taken by Armistead Nelson Wellford 1865 May 27 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Grant and Pardon of Armistead Nelson Wellford by the President of the United States, Andrew Johnson; signed by William Henry Seward 1865 May 29 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Certification of Oath taken by Armistead Nelson Wellford 1865 August 31 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - University School, Richmond Report Card for Robert Carter Wellford; University of Virginia Report Cards for Armistead Nelson Wellford 1869, 1897-1900 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Plans for remodeling Sabine Hall; 19th century drawing n.d. (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Book Plate of Robert Wormeley Carter n.d. (Box-folder 5:16)
  - "Negroes Baptized in Richmond County 1723-1724" n.d. (Box-folder 5:16)
  - 20th century Photograph of Sabine Hall interior n.d. (Box-folder 5:17)
- Series XI: Larger Bound Volumes
  - Waste Book of Landon Carter 1752-1758 (Box 5)
  - Waste Book of Landon Carter #2 1773-1777 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Agricultural Journal kept by Robert Wormeley Carter 1813-1860 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Mill Book kept by Robert Wormeley Carter, also containing a Register of Slaves 1831-1845 (Box-folder 6:3)
    containing mill accounts, 1831 July 2-ca. 1838; slave registers for 183?, 1838, 1844, and 1852; inventory of stock and tools at Poplar Hill (Sabine Hall), and House Farm; list of net profits, 1835-1844, for Poplar Hill, Mangorike, and House Farm; cement recipes; crops planted, 1822-1845, with commentary on them; clothing issues, 1839; wine accounts, 1836-1845; miscellaneous accounts of cloth, shoes, corn, and the like; pages 82-195 ripped out
  - Ledger kept by Robert Wormeley Carter containing accounts, household expenses, and personal expenses, with index 1832-1847 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Ledger kept by Robert Wormeley Carter containing accounts, household expenses, and personal expenses 1848-1857 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Agricultural Journal kept by Robert Wormeley Carter 1854 January-1857 June 30 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Physician's Account Ledger kept by Beverley R. Wellford 1856-1861 (Box 7)
  - Agricultural Journal kept by Robert Wormeley Carter 1860-1904 (Box-folder 7:1)
    containing Robert Wormley Carter's notes, 1860 January 4-1861 July 14; R.C. Wellford's agricultural diary and accounts, 1878 July 10-1904; and some miscellaneous accounts
  - Physician's Account Ledger kept by Beverley R. Wellford 1861-1866 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Index to Physician's Account Ledger kept by Beverley R. Wellford 1861-1866 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Miscellaneous copies of Carter documents ca. 1700s (Box-folder 7:3)
    copies, mostly of oversize or pre-repair documents already in this collection